so I've got three suitors that we can go
through two different topics and so
so this first Suitor is from the anguta
nikaya 573
and it's called one who lives the
teaching
and so this person is speaking asking
the Buddha sir they speak of one who
lives the teaching how is one who lives
in the teaching
and the Buddha replies take a monk who
is learning the teaching they spend
their days studying
they neglect Solitude and do not engage
in settling the mind
that monk is called one who studies a
lot not who won not one who lives the
teaching
furthermore among teachers in detail to
others what they have heard and studied
they spend their days expounding their
teaching but they neglect Solitude and
do not engage in settling the mind
that monk is called one who expounds a
lot not one who lives the teacher
furthermore a monk recites in detail the
teaching that they have heard and
learned they spend their days reciting
but they neglect Solitude and do not
engage in settling your mind
or a man who intentionally reflects upon
thinks about and considers the teaching
he has heard and learned they spend
their day reflecting on their teaching
but they neglect Solitude and do not
engage in settling the mind
and then take a monk who is studying the
teaching they don't spend their day studying
they don't spend their day studying
their teaching they don't neglect
Solitude and they engage in settling the
mind that's how monk is one who lives
the teaching thank you
so there's a few questions around us
so a person can go into great detail
with their studies like learning Pali
there's there's historical contexts of
the texts
etymological investigations statistical
analysis comparisons parallel map making
memorization categorization
and becoming a proliferated scholar
accredited by others who have done the
same yet still not be living or applying
yet still not be living or applying
their teaching but they are supposed to
be experts on it so
so
a dozen knowledge make you understand
the subject you are learning is such
scholarly work really an obstacle
and getting all that information well
yeah I think whoever asks the question
needs to differentiate knowledge and
information you can have a vast amount of
you can have a vast amount of
information collected that's the doesn't
mean you understood the subject you're
informed about
and in this case that's even more
obvious because the understanding of the
subject of the dhamma is measured by
sotopathy or higher
so since that's not the case then no
amount of knowledge is actually
knowledge that matters
is just information and references and
so on that can very much create an
impression in a conceited mind of being
fully kind of being an expert on a topic
kind of being an expert on a topic
because you you have learned every facet
every permutation of it but you haven't
understood it
um and uh
I think if somebody commits to to that
direction to that extent of
informational studies yeah I think it's
quite uh it's quite risky in a way
basically if you commit to such level of
collect information without having the
Right View first
you are going there with your conceit
which you agreed which you're craving
which your mental habits and
proliferations and then you're going to
arrive there thinking now you understood
everything because you turned every
stone upside down you investigated every
root of every word you memorize
everything so there is no more information there to
so there is no more information there to
gain in that sense so you would
genuinely feel like you arrive at the
complete understanding of the Buddhist
teaching while you're still a protection
and that's like one of the most blatant
contradictions in terms
so same like committing to a meditation
method or something or committing to a
Scholastic study without having
developed the Right View it's just gonna
increase your wrong views as simple as
that yeah really block your focus yeah there
yeah really block your focus yeah there
is because even if you start in the very
beginning before you have gone into
wrong directions you still have a lot of
things to undo
internally misconceived Notions
perceptions and so on until you can
actually even begin to understand the
direction where the dam applies
but in this case you would have
accumulated a lot more than you would
also have to undo and uh
generally is a kind of Unwritten rule is
that if you couldn't undo it when there
wasn't so much of a burden on you you're
probably not going to do it 20 years
later when you have accumulated on a
mountain of it
mountains of convictions and stuff
but if a person is honest
and they don't forsake the most
fundamental reason for the practice
which is freedom from suffering they
won't trade that too far so somebody
might have an inclination to learn more
in study technology but they will keep
this as a reference point
that that you know necessity of
understanding the nature of suffering
and being free from it as the measure of
understanding not a degree from a
householders university on Buddhist
studies
so it's like you can read uh
so we have access everybody has access
to the centers to all this information
and you've got information about
all these different genres and states in
a higher states of mind uh all these
kind of really complicated topics even
and I think that yeah the danger is if you
I think that yeah the danger is if you
don't
realize when you're reading these things
that's okay so have I have I done the
first things you know do I keep the
precepts do I keep essential straight
no but then why am I even thinking about
John and the eighth genre why I'm even going
and the eighth genre why I'm even going
that direction why do you even think
that any of this stuff applies to me
that any of this instruction applies to
me
ever met the necessary criteria to even
qualify myself for the application of
these practices monks
is it so many times before he hasn't
never thought meditation
to householders it was just not a thing
you want to Somali calm your mind yeah
recollect your unbroken virtue they're
collectible Ponder on it actively on your right View
Ponder on it actively on your right View
and so on and and you will have pleasant
abiding here and now as it is out of the
composure
but that's like you know that's the work
and then you can do that work as a
layperson as well but having developed a
view that the work is on the level of
meditation technique or something
you actually neglect the work that you
could actually do and benefit from and
you do the stuff that's just going to
end up being a cover-up to whatever you
haven't resolved internally in in terms
of your state to puttuition and not
knowing the escape from suffering and so
on
there's also an aspect about
what is your measure or reference point
of
understanding even the basic things like
um for example like you can go into
different definitions of the word vedana for
definitions of the word vedana for
example
like and look at you know how what it
meant or whatever in the context of the
time or something
but it's kind of obvious if you think
about it so what's the point of doing
this to understand
like there's a
what you should spend as much time as
possible contemplating
what it actually refers to in your in
your own experience like to spend as
much you know in a way it's kind of you
know correct like I should spend as much
time trying to understand the subjects that
trying to understand the subjects that
I'm trying to fully understand because
it's not through looking at a book that
I'm going to understand this subject
that's not why the the that's not where
that subject is in a way that's where
the description or the
information information is but then the
point is to
turn it into your own experience and try
to like use your own your own
your own experience as that reference
point for what is right and what is
wrong or what is there what is the
meaning of of the suitors because
otherwise it's abstract
yeah like the five presets and sense of
strength your
you're looking at the like data in your
experience right yeah but you still need
to to make the effort to look at the
veteran in your experience not in the
veterinary dictionary
yeah that's what I mean yeah like yeah
you need to keep a pleasure to be a
sense restraint but you could still
maintain this Scholastic attitude and
look for it out there and perfectly
restrained but I still study what others
people other people had to say on vedana
throughout the history to learn vedana
while I actually am experiencing redana
here and now that's kind of the point
but I don't trust that
as a reference of learning and insight I
trust the comprehensive Scholastic
consultation of whatever has been said before and
of whatever has been said before and
then drawing kind of the essence of it
and maybe coming up with you the ideas
of my own and that's like completely
wrong direction as wrong as watching
your nostrils just in a different way
yeah like it
there's this um another said it's the
second Sutter in the
SASE
where he's saying and it starts by just
saying those monks who have recently
gone forth are like are new to this done
and discipline
I think it it can be interpreted as
being or those who have not yes the
Right View
should be encouraged to develop Sati
padana as in to contemplate the
phenomenon of the body in order to and
then it says so as to uh
so as to fully understand
or so as to fully understand the body as
also is to fully understand the mind
and then it continues how like the then
the second the noble disciple is
encouraged to
um contemplates the body but having
having understood this he is
he is now doing it in order to like
develop the complete understanding of it
basically so it's like and then what's
interesting is like in the translations
that you read of this
it kind of makes it sound as though
you're just sitting in this state of
like uh
developing a state of concentration that
will magically enable you to see to see
the Miracles rather than it but it's
it's very obvious or it's very just kind
of clear if you read the thing it just
says you know if you want to fully
understand something spend as much of
your time being you know composed being
clear-headed contemplating contemplating
yes
etymological basis for these words but
it doesn't give that instruction look at
the history of these words it doesn't
look all of that can be helpful if you
already know where to look
but you will not necessarily find out
where to look if the only place you look
is the etymology is in history and
Scholastic study
because I mentioned it before there was
that like a long time ago and yeah you
start reading the sutas and then other
Pali and other things and
translations and then my own language
and in English language and in Pali
language and then you're trying to get
the idea but then I remember you just
don't do me like it's about
Consciousness I must have said this
before many times and it was like okay
but okay let's put aside all these
different words let me just use the
words that I know even in my own
language when I say consciousness
what do I refer to what am I referring
to there has to be something in this
experience that I'm designating by World
Consciousness so rather than dwelling on
the aspect of how that work came to be
and what it means for others and so on
no just in the most direct way I'm
telling you I am a conscious person what
am I referring to one aspect of this
experience of me and others am I
designating by saying I'm a conscious
person self-aware what part of this is
referred to
another reason that's completely unclear
because let me find something easier
than a webinar feeling oh
what am I referring to now I still are
clear and I realized then that's the
whole point they're calling whatever you
want they need to be understood not
redesignated and rebranded and
reinvestigated as I said through like a
historiological context or something
because the Notions in regard to those
five things that you start with form
feeling perception intentions
Consciousness you know the basic stuff
the Notions that you carry as a
unenlightened person
are the reason why you're unenlightened
they obstruct the nature of that which
you take to be yours
and you take to be used because you
don't see it as as unownable
and instead of undoing what you already
kind of holding and assuming you're just
piling up more
it's just yeah you learn one language
another one and another when you write a
paper and then compare the two and then
you add the third reference in great
great and it's endless in that way and
you still haven't actually cleared up
the very starting point when you use the
word from any language you pick to
designate Consciousness what phenomenon
are you referring to what is it describe
it in your own words
what are the properties of it what is
its nature
feeling form intentions same okay I've
had I've done this before like I just
okay what actually is Greed for example
what do I mean like what is and then
you're just like thinking about that
throughout the day it naturally kind of
um gives you a certain
broader perspective or a higher
perspective like when your mind wants to
uh go in a certain direction or be kind
of greedy it's not like okay I must not
do this and so okay oh that's greed okay
what so is this greed or is this what
feeling means and now you kind of not
are naturally kind of not on the level
of just you know
embodying it be becoming is you're
developing some perspective in regards
to us without it being this like
it's easier instances I think it
couldn't be for some people to not
become too wound up about not acting out
of unwholesome and so on
is like the two types of thoughts we
were talking about last week yeah
exactly the broad category but you
realize for that to not be an abstract
thing you need to invest them good
actually yeah clarifying and doing
things up to the point where you do
clearly see oh anything that partakes in
Greedy resolution category of
unwholesome anything that doesn't but
taking it category of wholesome
factually as a phenomenon you see you
see that nature of it
and so everybody can start that with as
an idea and then out of that external
idea they will try to do it but yeah
that's fine if you you know you begin
like that but the point is not to like
just stick to it blindly but to actually
stop referring to it as an external idea
and develop that internal reference
point no no I need to know why greater
version delusion ARA also yeah how
they're always felt and as we described
in the previous talk they always have a
nature of a trap
nature of pressure
of of burden of death and you realize
well that's actually
not good if it were good it wouldn't
need to be set up in such a devious
manner so that's why I don't trust it that's
so that's why I don't trust it that's
why I won't do it and that's something
you can see for yourself that's like
when the danger becomes apparent when
you suddenly recognize the Trap that you
haven't been seeing before and you've
been walking through and getting trapped
many times now you actually saw it and
then you learned how to say it
and then you'll avoid it naturally when
you see it as a trap yeah
but none of that will just magically
crystallize in your mind on a kind of
sticking to the precepts and so on or or
meditating diligently in the
Contemporary sense of technique and
concentration no that needs that's the
diligence that's the work the right type
of thinking abstaining from welcoming
the thoughts of a wholesome kind yeah
picking up Dharma
object I dumb themes that you will
actually Ponder and and clarify for
yourself like okay the Buddha said
culturally wholesome don't Calvin
wholesome what is wholesome
like now when I have these thoughts what
are they are they wholesome
whatever conclusion you come to okay now
reinvestigate that
so you actually have to actively engage
in in clarifying what what work needs to
be done
otherwise it wouldn't be a trap if if
you could kind of yeah I think if you
could discern it without that without
that um kind of continuous stage yeah
well you wouldn't have to go against the
grain is I think yeah that's the point
because because yeah the trust the whole
point is that it sort of limits you and
people kind of just stick synonyms and
they stumble upon Enlightenment one in
this direction and look sorry no it
can't happen by accident because you
have to perpetually swim against the
whole grain of your being the entire
nature everything it points that very
well for one reason or the other you are
going against it you are swimming
upwards for how long well are the faith for as
for how long well are the faith for as
long as it takes and then when things
are verified and seen for yourself then
of course you won't need any more
convincing this is a good week ikaya eight 63.
this is a good week ikaya eight 63.
and
it's called in brief so then a certain
bigger approached the lesson one paid
homage to him and said pante it would be
good if the blessed one would teach me
the Dharma in brief so that having heard
the dhamma from the best one I might
dwell alone withdrawn hateful Ardent and
resolute and then the bully replies it is in just
and then the bully replies it is in just
this way that some Hollow Men here make
requests of me but when the Dharma has
been explained they think only of
following me around and that first of
all saying it kind of relates to the
last one yeah you're just reading and
you know suitors after suits after suits
but not applying any of it yeah like you
you might as well be holding a view that
reading and getting inspired on a kind
of suit has ease the application
yeah and but practically you'll just be
following the suitors of the Buddha
around not doing it
because needing a constant access to the
source of inspiration
of the external client
so they they might not have had their
suitors like all the students we have
today but every store
kind of doing the same things sometimes
and then the monk says mate let the best
one teach me the download breathe let
the fortunate one teach me the Dominion
brief perhaps I might come to understand
the meaning
of the statements
so then the Buddha says in that case
Baker you should train yourself thus
my mind will be immovable and settled
internally I risen bad unwholesome States will not
I risen bad unwholesome States will not
overpower my mind
thus you should train yourself
do that there you go
so you realize why like I mean you you
can ask yourself why
if that's not enough instruction for you
why is that not enough
why is that insufficient
you realize well it's not because the
instructional lacks meat or Hardwood
it's because too many obstructions in
your mind that this is just too abstract
so you better start clearing up the mess
so that you can apply that
and everybody starts with some degree of
mess so
everybody has to do some cleaning
but it's uh and that should be like oh
that can be a reflection wait but why is
this not enough for my mind to to do it
to get inspired because because I don't
truly understand what I need to do
and I don't really understand because I
cannot measure the task given to me
because I don't I don't quite see where
it applies and I don't see where it
applies because I'm obviously
well not listening properly so to speak
in other words I'm listening to these
words but they don't mean the same thing
to me as they mentioned Buddha when he
instructed it when he refers to those
things mine they know the power and I'm
wholesome but those things are not
understood by me
so I better start understanding that so
that in this instruction can make sense
so that I can measure the task so that I
can actually apply myself and get the
results of it
so that's unpleasant work that's uh yeah
of course properly this
properly this
point I'd actually don't even
know what that means it's kind of a
it can be easy to just kind of take for
granted your own like first impression
of what you think that might mean and
then try and like do it which is
obviously the results okay that's why
they kind of initial and feel kind of
inspiring or something but then it would
sort of run out and it's like oh well I
need to get more instruction because I
don't really I've done a bit but now
yeah now I think I need more because you
didn't clarify at the beginning the what
that initial instruction really meant
and you could and you and you won't
clarify for as long as you think the
clarification uh comes from the outside
exactly like sometimes yeah maybe you
simply don't have enough information but
in cases like this you have that's
enough that's efficient otherwise it
wouldn't have given it as a
self-sufficient instruction
so the clarification of that instruction
then comes on the level of not further
Scholastic study but actually undoing
the basic misconceptions in regard to
the phenomenon of mind
Consciousness uh wholesome and wholesome
being overpowered overpowering and all
that yeah I mean doing that you know
trying to figure out what my mind will
be should be immovable settled
internally who isn't bad and wholesome
States will not overpower my mind so if
you're actually trying to do that and
doing that to try and apply that that
instruction will be you would see deeper
yeah deeper and deeper you wouldn't move
on because there is depth and the ending
of the practice but another thing to add
though is that even as a let's say
simple instruction as that as in not
very complex not many moving parts
uh doesn't matter how much you apply
yourself even if you're doing it what in
the way we're describing it it won't
work unless you have been restrained
beforehand um guarding of the centers keeping the
um guarding of the centers keeping the
presets being watchful and mindful you
just won't work and that's why the mind
would drift away as well it's because
because you're actually undermining it
you are unanchoring it from the right
context through your intentional acts
towards sensuality out of real will out
of hindrances
yeah so if you actually invest the work
there you won't need much of any
external inspiration to keep you
inspired on a topic or a theme of
practice the mind wanderth too far away
from it because you are not taking it
too far away from it with your actions
so that's another thing to consider if
like instruction like this but just
seems to kind of pass over my head and
mine doesn't leap leap into it and want
to think about it wants to contemplate
it well I think you might have to re
review your behavior by Body by speed my
mind how do you spend the rest of your
waking day what do you think you think
about things you're saying bodily
actions are they restrained thoroughly
withdrawn dried up
if not well you got your answer that's
when all this will apply
but yeah the season continues and it's
this the Buddha gives extra further
meditation exercises some instructions
he says
your mind is immovable and settled
internally and Arisen bad and wholesome
states did not overpower your mind then
you should train yourself
thus further so
so you've got to do that first so have
you passed there so why do you do that
first you do the
how do you measure how do you know
you're not overpowered by the so Arizona
wholesome States your mind is settled
but wholesome States arose yeah so
that's not up to you as we say often
okay so is this overpowering me or is it
not for whatever what do we do how do I
know am I am I still removable is this
movie so how do you know whether you're
so how do you know whether you're
overpowered or not what's the measure of
being overpowered can you just blink the
next moment is oh I'm overpowered
acting up my body speech online exactly
certainly by body and speech yeah you're
over poverty if you are taught if you
don't act out you're not overpower it
doesn't matter the amount of doubt they
might try to make you act out or clarify
it you realize well
I'm not like nah thus I'm not the one
being moved sure I'm feeling the
pressure of the unwholesome state
but I'm not acting up I'm not doing
anything on account of it it's there I'm
mindful of it that's it
I'm internally calm in regards you know
yeah internally calm means basically not
acting out does not mean internally not
feeling the pressure of an artisan and
wholesome States otherwise why would you
need to practice uh steadiness and not
being overwhelmed by it no you do feel
the weight of it that's kind of the
point so so it's like not not acting out
not liking our body or acting up with
speech okay well to that extent I was
moved but at least they denied my body
oh I didn't have the right body I didn't
talk about the speech okay mentally I'm
still trying to revolve around and get
rid of this doubt I'm acting out to that
extent let me stop that now as well at
least I didn't write down by speech and
my body
so it is a gradual training then you can
perfect the point
there is a pressure of the unwholesome
you're internally calm there is the
doubt to clarify whether you return on a
car or not and you recognize even that
now if you were to clarify it would be
acting out on account of discomfort and
you realize well by not clarifying it
I'm clarifying it by not engaging with a
clarification of my doubt I'm staying
unmoved and that's kind of the point
that even doubt wants me to resolve
so you stop using the middleman of
hindrances and acting out of them
so
once that's done once you've Yeah Yeah
unmoved by these things
it says then you can do these further
exercises and one of them is that drama
viharas I will develop and cultivate The
Liberation of Mind by friendliness or
not your will make it a vehicle a habit
a basis carry it out consolidated and
properly undertake it I would take up a
theme that now my mind would listen and
pay attention to and adhere to why well
because I attained it
yeah so you can see we always say like
you know the genre the whole practice
comes as a result of you overcoming the
hindrances and the standing then
wholesome thoroughly withdrawing it I
mean every description of Jannah says
thoroughly withdrawn from unwholesome
States from five hindrances on a later
occasion basically then he he dwells he
enters he dwells having antagona
on a later occasion after he's
thoroughly withdrawn quite secluded
whichever translation we're using means
you've done this work first thoroughly
without any residue without any
tolerating of the hindrances and and
acting out of them and then the mind
will listen and it will be inwardly calm
and then whether it's Jana or Brahma
vihara that's the order of development
but not like well I'll practice for Jana
Janik ecstatic absorption pleasure and
thus sensuality will fall away as a
result of that and this is the same
people thought oh I'm full of will will
so a practice meta so that these things
will fall away no no you gotta drop
those things first and then the mind can
develop meta on its own
yeah you you create that that
environment yeah yeah of course of
course it's not that it's not just
magically yeah as we said in the
previous that I have abandoned I have
relinquished I've given up the five
hindrances that uh
she's given them up to fully
understanding them and that's why now
she is John as it will
not other way around yeah and like
likewise with this one doesn't say he
develops Brahma viharas and then
exactly yeah and here is a technique for
Brahma vihara stick to it blindly and
you'll become immovable like a rocket no
hindrance can enter you and and no work
of contemplation and enduring the pain
or the pressure of our business stage
they're trying to abound you you will
have to endure wouldn't that be
wonderful yeah
until you snap yeah yeah because
basically you're just covering things up
hmm and it goes on further it says uh when
and it goes on further it says uh when
this samadhi has been developed and
cultivated by you in this way that's uh
composure of primary harvest the mind of
non-ill Will and so on
then you should develop this kind of
Somali with thinking and pondering
without thinking but only just pondering
develop it with our thinking and
Boundary develop it with Joy or letting
go of Joy accompanied with ease or a
company with Equanimity so
he's doing genres on top you know he's
able to practice genres alongside
grammarly homes
and when because this kind of so now
when you're able to do that even even
steadier when because samadhi has been thoroughly
when because samadhi has been thoroughly
divided by you in this way then you
should train yourself thus I will dwell
contemplating the body in the body
diligently clearly comprehending well
then you're qualified for setup Katana
yeah mindful having to move along and
mindful having to move along and
concerned and go to the world
yeah
and while you're doing that also do
because by that time there will be
absolutely no
obstruction or misconception left as we
started this talk with in regard to what
the bodies what the phenomena of the
body is what the phenomena the feeling
is intentions mind it would have all
been cleared and clarified and endured
sufficiently for you to become very familiar with its
for you to become very familiar with its
nature
you would say you can develop yeah
the nature of the body yeah
yeah exactly make it your vehicle yeah
you you travel around with that thing in
there but the thing is again it's not
just a theme on the level of oh yeah I
make sure I can understand what the
description of what is body for what it
is it's nature no no it's seeing that it
started as an external instruction
you know the honorability that what body
is subjected to it's like position in
this world seeing that when you look at
this body that's what you see
so it's it's a direct recognition of
what you learned from before through the
Mind development described it precedes
it all
so now just applying these abstract
Notions of impermanence and Anita and so
on they will somehow permeate these
things and dissolve the roots of uh
great diversion and delusion no no you
you need to pull them out you need to
find them
cut for them find them
take them all out
one by one basically
until all the work is done and then you
can rest
so the suit Ends by saying when biku
this composure the samadhi has been developed
composure the samadhi has been developed
and well developed by you then wherever
you whenever you walk you will walk at
ease where do you stand sit or lie down
you will lie down at ease
no more problems no problems